Guide to the Bruce J. Zobel Papers, 1937-2008 MC 00259
Special Collections Research Center
- Photographs and Slides, Undated; MC 00259 Series 12; 8.0 Linear feet; 16 boxes
  - Slides
    - Secondary Slides
      - United States and Canada: Select Trees (Album 173, Folder 5)
      - United States and Canada: Provenance (Album 173, Folder 6)
      - United States and Canada: Seed Orchard (Album 173, Folder 7)
      - United States and Canada: Plantations (Album 174, Folder 1)
      - United States and Canada: Site Preparation (Album 174, Folder 2)
      - United States and Canada: Logging (Album 174, Folder 3)
      - United States and Canada: Forest Management (Album 174, Folder 4)
      - United States and Canada: Nursery (Album 174, Folder 5)
      - United States and Canada: Species (Album 174, Folder 6)
      - United States and Canada: Biology and Biotech (Album 174, Folder 7)
      - United States and Canada: Natural Stands (Album 174, Folder 8)
      - United States and Canada: Eucalyptus (Album 174, Folder 9)
      - United States and Canada: Pests (Album 175, Folder 1)
      - United States and Canada: Flowering (Album 175, Folder 2)
      - United States and Canada: Pollen (Album 175, Folder 3)
      - United States and Canada: Heritability Study (Album 175, Folder 4)
      - United States and Canada: Equipment (Album 175, Folder 5)
      - United States and Canada: Wood (Album 175, Folder 6)
      - United States and Canada: Cone and Seed Collection (Album 175, Folder 7)
      - United States and Canada: Buildings (Album 176, Folder 1)
      - United States and Canada: Animals (Album 176, Folder 2)
      - United States and Canada: Texas (Album 176, Folder 3)
      - United States and Canada: Coulter and Jefferson Pine (Album 176, Folder 4)
      - United States and Canada: Vegetative Proppgation (Album 176, Folder 5)
      - United States and Canada: Problems (Album 176, Folder 6)
      - United States and Canada: Naval Stores (Album 176, Folder 7)
      - United States and Canada: Tree Form (Album 176, Folder 8)
      - United States and Canada: People and Short Courses (Album 176, Folder 9)
      - United States and Canada: Flowering II (Album 176, Folder 10)
      - United States and Canada: Agroforestry (Album 176, Folder 11)
      - Australia (Album 177, Folder 1)
      - Brazil- Amazon (Album 177, Folder 2)
      - Brazil- Amcel (Album 177, Folder 3)
      - Brazil- Aracruz (Album 177, Folder 4)
      - Brazil- CVRD (Album 177, Folder 5)
      - Brazil- Embrasca (Album 177, Folder 6)
      - Brazil- Jari (Album 177, Folder 7)
      - Brazil- Pains (Album 177, Folder 8)
      - Brazil- Southern Brazil (Album 177, Folder 9)
      - Canada- Irving (Album 178, Folder 1)
      - Canada- Newfoundland (Album 178, Folder 2)
      - Canada- Nova Scotia (Album 178, Folder 3)
      - Canada- Prince Edward Island (Album 178, Folder 4)
      - Canada- Saskatchewan (Album 178, Folder 5)
      - Canada- St. Anne-Nackowic (Album 178, Folder 6)
      - Chile (Album 178, Folder 7)
      - Colombia- Atrata and Llanos (Album 178, Folder 8)
      - Colombia- General (1 of 2) (Album 178, Folder 9)
      - Colombia- General (2 of 2) (Album 179, Folder 1)
      - Colombia- Carton de Colombia (Album 179, Folder 2)
      - Colombia- Jungle (Album 179, Folder 3)
      - Colombia- Pizano and Monterrey Forestal (Album 179, Folder 4)
      - Costa Rica (Album 179, Folder 5)
      - Guatamala (Album 179, Folder 6)
      - Holland and Belgium (Album 179, Folder 7)
      - Indonesia (Album 180, Folder 1)
      - Italy and Spain (Album 180, Folder 2)
      - Mexico (Album 180, Folder 3)
      - New Zealand (Album 180, Folder 4)
      - Northern Europe (mixed) (Album 180, Folder 5)
      - Norway (Album 180, Folder 6)
      - Rhodesia and Zimbawbe (Album 180, Folder 7)
      - South Africa- Animals (Album 180, Folder 8)
      - South Africa- General (Album 180, Folder 9)
      - Sweden- General (Album 180, Folder 10)
      - Sweden- Stora (Album 180, Folder 11)
      - Venezuela- Conare (Album 181, Folder 1)
      - Venezuela- Guayamure (Album 181, Folder 2)
      - Venezuela- Miscellaneous (Album 181, Folder 3)
      - Venezuela- Papeles (Album 181, Folder 4)
      - Venezuela- Proforca (Album 181, Folder 5)
- Scrapbooks, 1940, circa 2001; MC 00259 Series 13
  This brief series contains a scrapbook of wildflower samples, and a scrapbook assembled by colleagues on the occasion of Zobel's retirement.
  - Collection of Wildflowers, 1940 (Box 182)
  - Retirement Party Scrapbook (Box 182)
- Artifacts, Undated; MC 00259 Series 14
  This series contains items used in Zobel's teaching career, such as wood and pine cone samples. It also contains awards, plaques, trophies, and other gifts given to Zobel in appreciation for his contributions to forestry.
  - Cross Section
    - Loblolly pine cross section, undated (Box 183)
      Special fast grown, high density loblolly pine, developed by selection and breeding
  - Pinecones
    These cones are from Zobel's Ph.D. research, conducted from 1949 to 1951. All cones were taken from natural stands. All are labeled with numbers.
    - The Coulter pine parent, Item no. 2 (Box 184)
    - The Jeffrey pine parent, Item no. 3 (Box 184)
    - One form of the Coulter-Jeffrey hybrid, Item no. 4 (Box 184)
    - Another form of the Coulter-Jeffrey hybrid, Item no. 5 (Box 184)
    - A third form of the Coulter-Jeffrey hybrid, Item no. 6 (Box 184)
    - The hybrid backcrossed to Coulter pine, Item no. 7 (Box 184)
    - The hybrid backcrossed to Jeffrey pine, Item no. 8 (Box 184)
    - Another hybrid backcrossed to Coulter pine, Item no. 9 (Box 184)
    - Pure Coulter pine from a poor site, Item no. 10 (Box 184)
    - Pure Jeffrey pine from a poor site, Item no. 11 (Box 184)
    - Yearling conelets showing the shape of the scales in the coulter and jeffrey parents and the intermediacy in the hybrid, Item no. 1 (Box 185)
  - Wood specimens used in teaching
    The wood specimens are labeled with numbers.
    - Low density wood, Item no. 1a (Box 185)
    - Medium density wood, Item no. 1b (Box 185)
    - High density wood, Item no. 1c (Box 185)
    - Knot form, large and small, Item no. 2 (Box 185)
    - Interlocked grain--sweet gum, Item no. 3 (Box 185)
    - Normal growth pattern, Item no. 4 (Box 185)
    - 6-year-old P. caribaea - from the Amazon, Item no. 5 (Box 185)
    - Loblolly pine, showing juvenile wood, Item no. 6 (Box 185)
    - Compression wood in loblolly pine, Item no. 7 (Box 185)
    - Needle traces in foxtail stem of P. caribaea, Item no. 8 (Box 185)
    - Fir from Newfoundland, showing release from thinning, Item no. 9 (Box 185)
    - Increment core showing juvenile wood, Item no. 10 (Box 185)
    - Compression caused by aphids--loblolly in South Africa, Item no. 11 (Box 185)
    - How not to make a section--missed the pith, Item no. 12 (Box 185)
    - How to take a section through the pith, Item no. 13 (Box 185)
    - Fir from Newfoundland not released (see #9), Item no. 14 (Box 185)
    - Compression wood from a straight tree, Item no. 15 (Box 185)
    - Small and large limb, Item no. 16 (Box 185)
    - Beaver damage, Item no. 17 (Box 185)
  - Awards and Plaques
    - Certificate of Appreciation from the American Forestry Association, October 31, 1979 (Box 186)
    - State of North Carolina Board of Registration for Foresters Registration Certificate, June 1976 (Box 186)
    - Bruce and Barbara Zobel Endowment plaque, 1998 (Box 186)
    - Plaque of Appreciation for Tropical Forestry Short Course, March 19, 1985 (Box 186)
    - NCSU Outstanding Extension Service Award (Box 186)
    - Gamma Delta Sigma International Award for Distinguished Service to Agriculture, 1980 (Box 187)
    - Award from the Research and Development Division of TAPPI, November 10, 1973 (Box 187)
    - Technical Association of the Pulp and Paper Industry Fellow plaque, March 6, 1973 (Box 187)
    - Forest Farmer tribute, June 1977 (Box 188)
    - Institute of Forest Genetics plaque, August 2001 (Box 188)
    - TAPPI medal plaque, February 27, 1975 (Box 188)
    - 2 unidentified reels of film (Box 188)
    - Commemoration of the First Noranda Tree Improvement Conference, February 27, 1990 (Box 189)
    - Forest Farmer Annual Award, May 18, 1978 (Box 189)
    - Society of American Foresters Fellow plaque, 1969 (Box 190)
    - Annual Meeting of the Florida Forestry Association plaque, September 14, 1976 - September 15, 1976 (Box 190)
    - U.S. Steel plaque, presented by Fortune, May 1995 (Box 191)
    - Man of the Year, N.C. Forestry Association plaque, 1982 (Box 191)
    - Artifacts (Box 192)
    - Artifacts (Box 193)
    - Artifacts (Box 194)
    - Artifacts (Box 194)
    - Artifacts (Box 196)
    - "Genetic freak" tree sample (Box 197)
    - Bowling Pin (Box 198)
    - Carved wooden ax item given to Zobel by graduate students (Box 199)
    - Trophy given to Zobel by the North Carolina Wildlife Federation (Box 200)
    - Alexander Quarles Holladay Medal for Excellence, certificate, 2004 (Box 383, Folder 24)
    - TAPPI Golden Anniversary Certificate, 2007 (Box 383, Folder 25)
    - North Carolina State University College of Natural Resources 50 Years of Service certificate, 2007 (Box 383, Folder 26)
- Card Index, MC 00259 Series 15
  Cards in this index reference full-text reprinted articles in Series 16. This card index was created by Zobel, and is organized according to a numbering system that he instituted. There are two subseries of cards in this index system; the first subseries primarily references articles printed prior to 1957, the second subseries references articles mostly printed from 1957 onward. Both series were divided by Zobel into subject indexes and author indexes, allowing reference access by either means. Subject index cards in both subseries marked with a red X indicate a full-text reprint of that article is available in Series 16.
  - 4 in. x 6 in. Cards, pre-, 1957
    - Subject index, 8.111-8.1145, cards; 4 in. x 6 in (Cardbox 230)
    - Subject index, 8.1146-8.1157, cards; 4 in. x 6 in (Cardbox 231)
    - Subject index, 8.1157-8.132, cards; 4 in. x 6 in (Cardbox 232)
    - Subject index, 8.1321-8.162, cards; 4 in. x 6 in (Cardbox 233)
    - Subject index, 8.31-8.732, cards; 4 in. x 6 in (Cardbox 234)
    - Alphabetic index, A - Che, cards; 4 in. x 6 in (Cardbox 234)
    - Alphabetic index, Chi - K, cards; 4 in. x 6 in (Cardbox 235)
    - Alphabetic index, L - Schr, cards; 4 in. x 6 in (Cardbox 236)
    - Alphabetic index, Schu - Z, cards; 4 in. x 6 in (Cardbox 237)
  - 5 in. x 8 in. Cards, 1957-1998
    - Subject index, 8.111-8.1121, cards; 5 in. x 8 in. (Cardbox 201)
    - Subject index, 8.11212-8.1133, cards; 5 in. x 8 in (Cardbox 202)
    - Subject index, 8.11331-8.11447, cards; 5 in. x 8 in (Cardbox 203)
    - Subject index, 8.11448-8.11461, cards; 5 in. x 8 in (Cardbox 204)
    - Subject index, 8.114 -8.11494, cards; 5 in. x 8 in (Cardbox 205)
    - Subject index, 8.11495-8.1154, cards; 5 in. x 8 in (Cardbox 206)
    - Subject index, 8.1154-8.1158, cards; 5 in. x 8 in (Cardbox 207)
    - Subject index, 8.1159-8.11711, cards; 5 in. x 8 in (Cardbox 208)
    - Subject index, 8.11712-8.122, cards; 5 in. x 8 in (Cardbox 209)
    - Subject index, 8.1221-8.12226, cards; 5 in. x 8 in (Cardbox 210)
    - Subject index, 8.12227-8.134, cards; 5 in. x 8 in (Cardbox 211)
    - Subject index, 8.134-8.1423, cards; 5 in. x 8 in (Cardbox 212)
    - Subject index, 8.143-8.156, cards; 5 in. x 8 in (Cardbox 213)
    - Subject index, 8.157-8.36, cards; 5 in. x 8 in (Cardbox 214)
    - Subject index, 8.36-8.58, cards; 5 in. x 8 in (Cardbox 215)
    - Subject index, 8.65-8.70, cards; 5 in. x 8 in (Cardbox 216)
    - Alphabetic index, A - Barnes, cards; 5 in. x 8 in (Cardbox 216)
    - Alphabetic index, Barnett - Byrd, cards; 5 in. x 8 in (Cardbox 217)
    - Alphabetic index, C - Derr, cards; 5 in. x 8 in (Cardbox 218)
    - Alphabetic index, Derr - Fram, cards; 5 in. x 8 in (Cardbox 219)
    - Alphabetic index, Fran - Harris, G., cards; 5 in. x 8 in (Cardbox 220)
    - Alphabetic index, Harris, H. - Johnson, cards; 5 in. x 8 in (Cardbox 221)
    - Alphabetic index, Johnsson - K, cards; 5 in. x 8 in (Cardbox 222)
    - Alphabetic index, L - Manwiller, cards; 5 in. x 8 in (Cardbox 223)
    - Alphabetic index, Manwiller - N, cards; 5 in. x 8 in (Cardbox 224)
    - Alphabetic index, O - Robert, cards; 5 in. x 8 in (Cardbox 225)
    - Alphabetic index, Roberts - Sillen, cards; 5 in. x 8 in (Cardbox 226)
    - Alphabetic index, Silliman - Tig, cards; 5 in. x 8 in (Cardbox 227)
    - Alphabetic index, Tim - Wi, cards; 5 in. x 8 in (Cardbox 228)
    - Alphabetic index, Wo - Z, cards; 5 in. x 8 in (Cardbox 229)
- Reprints, MC 00259 Series 16
  This series contains reprints of some of the articles indexed in Series 15; the subject index cards from Series 15 marked with a red X indicate the presence of a full-text article in this series. Articles in this series are ordered according to the numerical index scheme Zobel created, these numbers appear in parentheses following each subseries title. Zobel's organization of this index follows a hierarchical format; it should be noted here that for ease of reference, topics are listed without representation of that hierarchy.
  Additions were incorporated into this series in 2007. Articles added to the collection are arranged in alphabetical order by author, then by title, if no author is given.
  List of reprints
- Life's influences for children, undated (Halfbox 387)